<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<territory>
    <id>227</id>
    <old-id>svalbard</old-id>
    <short-form-name>Svalbard</short-form-name>
    <long-form-name type="none"/>
    <variants>
        <variant>
            <variant-id>227_1</variant-id>
            <variant-name>Spitsbergen</variant-name>
            <valid-since type="pre-1776">1775</valid-since>
            <valid-until type="present">9999</valid-until>
            <note></note>
        </variant>
    </variants>
    <type-of-territory>dependency-or-area-of-special-sovereignty</type-of-territory>
    <valid-since type="pre-1776">1775</valid-since>
    <valid-until type="present">9999</valid-until>
    <exists-on-todays-map>true</exists-on-todays-map>
    <predecessors type="none"/>
    <successors/>
    <notes>Although it may have been encountered by Icelandic sailors in the late 1190s (and claims
        of first contact were made by Russian and United Kingdom authorities), the first official
        record was put down by Dutch explorer William Barents in 1596. Svalbard was first settled by
        whalers in the early 1600s. Over the subsequent centuries, various nations and corporate
        interests established claims upon the archipelago–which was rich in whales, walrus, and
        coal. Colonies associated with various nations and corporations were established at this
        time–the Dutch, Danish, and United Kingdom made exclusive claims upon the islands at
        various times but were never able to enforce them thanks to the geographic isolation and
        extreme climate of the area. An informal arrangement persisted where particular bays and
        villages were operated exclusively by different national and corporate bodies. Over time,
        additional nations and corporations supported by national governments (particularly Norway,
        Russia, and the United States) established outposts in Svalbard. In 1872, Sweden-Norway and
        Russia exchanged notes declaring the territory a terra nullius-a ‘no man’s land’ which had
        never been and was not presently subject to the sovereignty of any state. A draft convention
        was prepared in 1912 formalized the territory’s status and proclaimed that it could not be
        annexed by any state. This anarchic state of affairs proved untenable in due course–most
        particularly when various companies began to claim mining rights in the early 1900s–and a
        conference was assembled in Christiana (present day Oslo) in June 1914 to determine control
        of the islands. While the assembled nations could not agree (either here or in a series of
        subsequent conferences) which nation should possess it, all previous claims were held to be
        void and the terra nullius status upheld. This highly unusual state of affairs attracted the
        interest of no less a luminary than future Secretary of State Robert Lansing who wrote of
        “This extraordinary political state of the islands, to which a parallel will be hard to find
        in modern times.” In 1920, as part of the post World War I Versailles process, Svalbard was
        granted to Norway under the terms of the Svalbard Treaty. This grant was somewhat limited as
        the treaty contained equal enjoyment and liberty of access provisions for signatories and
        functionally created a demilitarized zone around the islands. Furthermore, not all Norwegian
        laws apply to Svalbard.</notes>
    <sources>
        <source>http://www.britannica.com/EBchecked/topic/575921/Svalbard</source>
        <source>http://openscholarship.wustl.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1564&amp;context=law_globalstudies</source>
        
     </sources>
</territory>
