<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<territory>
    <id>307</id>
    <old-id/>
    <short-form-name>Fulani Empire</short-form-name>
    <long-form-name type="none"/>
    <variants>
        <variant>
            <variant-id>307_1</variant-id>
            <variant-name>Sokoto Empire</variant-name>
            <valid-since>1804</valid-since>
            <valid-until>1904</valid-until>
            <note/>
        </variant>
    </variants>
    <type-of-territory>independent-state</type-of-territory>
    <valid-since>1804</valid-since>
    <valid-until>1904</valid-until>
    <exists-on-todays-map>false</exists-on-todays-map>
    <predecessors>
        <predecessor rel="split">308</predecessor>
    </predecessors>
    <successors>
        <successor rel="merger">302</successor>
    </successors>
    <notes>Fulani Muslim scholar (mallam) Usman dan Fodio initiated a revolutionary jihad in the
        Hausa state of Gobir in 1804, leading by 1808 to an overthrow of most of the Hausa states in
        Hausaland (northern Nigeria), some of which had formerly been under the Empire of Bornu to
        the east. The new Fulani Kingdom (or “Empire”) that arose came to be known also as the
        Sokoto Caliphate, after its capital at Sokoto founded in 1809. The caliphate/empire was a
        confederation of emirates in the former Hausa states / kingdoms, and was split into eastern
        and western divisions, under twin capitals at Sokoto and Gwandu (though Sokoto retained
        relative primacy). The empire/kingdom grew with time, e.g., incorporating Ilorin by the
        1830’s and establishing Adamawa by the mid-19th century. According to one account, the
        Fulani Empire at its peak was the largest empire in Africa since the fall of the Songhai
        (Songhay) Empire in 1591, extending 1500 kilometers from parts of modern-day Burkina Faso,
        through Nigeria, into parts of modern-Day Cameroon. The British gradually brought the former
        Fulani Empire/Sokoto Caliphate under British control between roughly 1900, when the
        Protectorate of Northern Nigeria was established, and 1903, the year when the British Royal
        West African Frontier Force mounted assaults on Kano and Sokoto.</notes>
    <sources>
        <source>https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/ni.html</source>
        <source>http://www.britannica.com/place/Nigeria</source>
        <source>https://www.loc.gov/item/89600361/</source>
    </sources>
</territory>
