<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<territory>
    <id>372</id>
    <old-id/>
    <short-form-name>Mauritius</short-form-name>
    <long-form-name type="none"/>
    <variants>
        <variant>
            <variant-id>372_1</variant-id>
            <variant-name>Port Louis</variant-name>
            <valid-since type="pre-1776">1775</valid-since>
            <valid-until>1968</valid-until>
            <note/>
        </variant>
    </variants>
    <type-of-territory>dependency-or-area-of-special-sovereignty</type-of-territory>
    <valid-since type="pre-1776">1775</valid-since>
    <valid-until>1968</valid-until>
    <exists-on-todays-map>false</exists-on-todays-map>
    <predecessors>
        <predecessor rel="incorporation">629</predecessor>
    </predecessors>
    <successors>
        <successor rel="independence">153</successor>
        <successor rel="split">629</successor>
    </successors>
    <notes>Claimed for France by the French East India Company in 1715. Mauritius had been abandoned
        by the Dutch in 1710, after they had presided over the extinction of the dodo bird, among
        other things. In 1764 (some sources say 1767), Mauritius became a French crown colony. In
        1810, during the Napoleonic wars, a British fleet of 70 ships landed 10,000 soldiers on
        Mauritius, and French officials surrendered the colony to the British. Britain’s sovereignty
        over Mauritius was confirmed in the 1814 Treaty of Paris. In 1810, during the Napoleonic
        wars, a British fleet of 70 ships landed 10,000 soldiers on Mauritius, and French officials
        surrendered the colony to the British. Britain’s sovereignty over Mauritius was confirmed in
        the 1814 Treaty of Paris, which also conferred the colony of the Seychelles to Britain.
        Britain administered the Seychelles as a dependency of Mauritius from 1814 to 1903. In 1903,
        Seychelles became its own British crown colony and was separated from Mauritius, though a
        few outlying islands remained with Mauritius for a time. Coetivy Island was transferred from
        Mauritius to the Seychelles in 1908, and the Farquhar Islands were transferred from
        Mauritius to the Seychelles in 1922. In 1965 Britain transferred one of Mauritius’s outlying
        territories, the Chagos Archipelago (including the Diego Garcia atoll), to the newly created
        British Indian Ocean Territory. Mauritius became an independent state within the (British)
        Commonwealth of Nations on March 12, 1968.</notes>
    <sources>
        <source>https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/mp.html</source>
        <source>http://www.britannica.com/place/Mauritius</source>
        <source>https://www.loc.gov/item/95016570/</source>
    </sources>
</territory>
