<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<territory>
    <id>374</id>
    <old-id/>
    <short-form-name>Papal States</short-form-name>
    <long-form-name type="none"/>
    <variants/>
    <type-of-territory>independent-state</type-of-territory>
    <valid-since type="pre-1776">1775</valid-since>
    <valid-until>1870</valid-until>
    <exists-on-todays-map>false</exists-on-todays-map>
    <predecessors type="none"/>
    <successors>
        <successor rel="incorporation">116</successor>
    </successors>
    <notes>At the height of their temporal power, the Popes controlled a significant amount of
        territory in northern Italy. On February 15, 1798, a French army captured Rome and installed
        a short-lived Roman Republic. The Papal States were restored subsequent to Neapolitan
        recapture of Rome on 30 September 1799. In the 1809 Schönbrunn Palace Declarations Napoleon
        reproached the Popes and ordered the Papal States (which had been recaptured by France)
        annexed into the French Empire. The fall of Napoleon resulted in the restoration of the
        states in 1814. Demonstrations in November 1848 led Pope Pius IX to flee from Rome; in
        February 1849 a new Roman Republic was established led by Italian nationalist dissidents.
        The new republic fell in July thanks to a siege conducted by a French army sent by Louis-
        Napoleon. As momentum towards Italian unification increased in the 1860s, various provinces
        of the Papal States were annexed by other Italian powers. Napoleon III maintained an army in
        Rome which protected the Papal States from annexation after the creation of the Kingdom of
        Italy in 1861. However, with the outbreak of the Franco-Prussian War in 1870 the French army
        was withdrawn and Rome taken by Italian forces on 20 September 1870. While the Papal States
        were not legally integrated into Italy until October 1871, they de facto ceased to exist as
        of this point.</notes>
    <sources>
        <source>https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/it.html</source>
        <source>http://britannica.com/place/Italy</source>
    </sources>
</territory>
