<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<territory>
    <id>42</id>
    <old-id>canada</old-id>
    <short-form-name>Canada</short-form-name>
    <long-form-name>Dominion of Canada</long-form-name>
    <variants/>
    <type-of-territory>independent-state</type-of-territory>
    <valid-since>1867</valid-since>
    <valid-until>9999</valid-until>
    <exists-on-todays-map>true</exists-on-todays-map>
    <predecessors>
        <predecessor rel="merger">303</predecessor>
        <predecessor rel="merger">578</predecessor>
        <predecessor rel="merger">580</predecessor>
        <predecessor rel="merger">581</predecessor>
        <predecessor rel="merger">584</predecessor>
        <predecessor rel="merger">585</predecessor>
        <predecessor rel="merger">586</predecessor>
    </predecessors>
    <successors/>
    <notes>In 1867, Canada was created as a self-governing dominion with domestic sovereignty out of
        the merger of three colonies, Canada, Nova Scotia, and New Brunswick. 
        In 1870, Rupert’s
        Land, a huge swath of territory owned by the Hudson’s Bay Company that had been purchased by
        the Canadian government, was incorporated into Canada. In 1871, the colony of British
        Columbia joined Canada. In 1873, the colony of Prince Edward Island joined Canada. In
        1949, the dominion of Newfoundland joined
        Canada. While Canada traces its status as an independent nation back to 1867, 
        the country acquired independence in stages. When it was created in 1867, Canada enjoyed
        only sovereignty over domestic affairs: it was still a part of the British Empire, meaning
        London directed its foreign policy. During the 1920s, Canada acquired sovereignty over its
        external affairs, culminating in the United Kingdom’s acceptance of Canada’s external
        sovereignty with the 1926 Balfour Declaration and the 1931 Statute of Westminster. Finally, in 1982,
        the United Kingdom passed the Canada Act, which gave
        effect to the Constitution Act, 1982, representing the patriation of Canada’s constitution.
        The United States recognized Canada’s independence in 1927.</notes>
    <sources>
        <source>https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/ca.html</source>
        <source>http://history.state.gov/countries/canada</source>
        <source>Robert Bothwell, The Penguin History of Canada (Penguin, 2007)</source>
        <source>http://www.thecanadianencyclopedia.ca/en/article/constitution-act-1982/</source>
    </sources>
</territory>
