<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<territory>
    <id>425</id>
    <old-id/>
    <short-form-name>Emirate of Brakna</short-form-name>
    <long-form-name type="none"/>
    <variants/>
    <type-of-territory>independent-state</type-of-territory>
    <valid-since type="pre-1776">1775</valid-since>
    <valid-until>1904</valid-until>
    <exists-on-todays-map>false</exists-on-todays-map>
    <predecessors type="none"/>
    <successors>
        <successor rel="incorporation">423</successor>
    </successors>
    <notes>Although the Treaty of Paris in 1814 recognized French sovereignty over the area that is
        now Mauritania, France only briefly exercised actual jurisdiction and control over portions
        of the region in the mid-19th century, and did not consistently do so until the beginning of
        the 20th century. Accordingly, various Maure groups and emirates (Trarza, Brakna, Tagant,
        Adrar), some of which engaged in treaties with the French, effectively continued to maintain
        sovereignty or suzerainty in the region throughout much of this period. The French colonial
        administration based in Senegal sporadically came into conflict with the Emirates of Trarza
        and Brakna throughout the 19th century, particularly in 1825 and 1855, resulting in
        intermittent periods of French control over portions of what is now Mauritania. By treaty
        following a French military victory in 1856, the Emirates of Trarza and Brakna conceded a
        French protectorate over their emirates and acknowledged French sovereignty over the
        northern bank of the Senegal River. French officials subsequently surveyed portions of
        western and southern Mauritania, including Adrar. By the 1870’s, however, the French no
        longer exerted active control or governance over present-day Mauritania. In 1901, French
        officials began an active effort to “peacefully” assert sovereignty throughout what is now
        Mauritania. Brakna came under French control in February 1904.</notes>
    <sources>
        <source>https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/mr.html</source>
        <source>https://www.loc.gov/item/89600361/</source>
        <source>http://britannica.com/place/Mauritania</source>
    </sources>
</territory>
