<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<territory>
    <id>504</id>
    <old-id/>
    <short-form-name>Niger</short-form-name>
    <long-form-name>Territory of the Niger</long-form-name>
    <variants/>
    <type-of-territory>dependency-or-area-of-special-sovereignty</type-of-territory>
    <valid-since>1900</valid-since>
    <valid-until>1960</valid-until>
    <exists-on-todays-map>false</exists-on-todays-map>
    <predecessors>
        <predecessor rel="incorporation">505</predecessor>
    </predecessors>
    <successors>
        <successor rel="incorporation">510</successor>
    </successors>
    <notes>French expeditions in the Niger began in the late 19th century and led to the
        establishment of a French “Middle Niger Circle” north of Niamey in 1898. A major French
        military campaign to assert military control over the region began in 1899. Immediately
        thereafter, several French administrative and military jurisdictions were established, but
        their precise jurisdictions and relationships to one another are not clear from the sources
        consulted. These French jurisdictions included: the “Cercle du Djerma,” established in
        western Niger on October 11, 1900; the French Third Military Territory for the Central
        Sudan, established on December 20, 1900, and provisionally headquartered north of Niamey in
        the same town as the Cercle du Djerma; and the Military Territory of Zinder, established on
        January 1, 1901, with headquarters in Zinder (eastern/southern Niger). These jurisdictions
        may have been part of a single French military territory by as early as 1903, as sources
        refer to the headquarters of “the military territory” moving back and forth between Niamey
        and Zinder on several occasions beginning that year. The “Territoire Militaire du Niger”
        (Military Territory of the Niger) was established on June 22, 1910, and appears to have
        consolidated these prior French administrative and military jurisdictions in the region. The
        Colony of the Niger was established July 1, 1922. On August 22, 1945, it became a French
        Overseas Territory, which afforded greater forms of self-governance. The colony became the
        independent Republic of Niger on August 3, 1960.</notes>
    <sources>
        <source>https://www.britannica.com/place/Niger</source>
        <source>https://www.britannica.com/place/French-West-Africa</source>
    </sources>
</territory>
