<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<territory>
    <id>510</id>
    <old-id>south-west-africa-1990</old-id>
    <short-form-name>South-West Africa</short-form-name>
    <long-form-name type="none"/>
    <variants>
        <variant>
            <variant-id>510_1</variant-id>
            <variant-name>German South West Africa</variant-name>
            <valid-since>1884</valid-since>
            <valid-until>1915</valid-until>
            <note/>
        </variant>
    </variants>
    <type-of-territory>dependency-or-area-of-special-sovereignty</type-of-territory>
    <valid-since>1884</valid-since>
    <valid-until>1990</valid-until>
    <exists-on-todays-map>false</exists-on-todays-map>
    <predecessors>
        <predecessor rel="incorporation">511</predecessor>
        <predecessor rel="incorporation">502</predecessor>
        <predecessor rel="incorporation">503</predecessor>
    </predecessors>
    <successors>
        <successor rel="independence">165</successor>
    </successors>
    <notes>On April 24, 1884, Germany formally declared “Lüderitzland” to be a protectorate of the
        German Empire.  Initially, the extent of German control was only a small area around
        Lüderitz Bay. Through a series of purchases and “protective treaties” with African leaders
        in 1884-1885, Germany declared an expanded German protectorate over not just Lüderitz Bay
        and the coastal areas, but also the Red Nation, Great Namaqualand, Hereroland, and other
        tribes (such as the Damara) and geographic areas extending over the southern and central
        portions of present-day Namibia.  A German Commissioner was appointed in August 1885, which
        may have coincided with the first use of the name, German South West Africa. 
        Representatives of the Namibian tribal nations, however, did not interpret the treaties to
        mean a relinquishment of their sovereignty, and subsequently renounced some of the
        agreements (e.g., in 1888 the Hereros renounced their 1885 protectorate agreement with
        Germany).  Between 1886 and 1890 Germany entered into agreements with Portugal and Britain
        that established the colonial boundaries of present-day Namibia, and Germany laid claim to
        and officially annexed the entire area in 1890, after bringing in military troops a year
        earlier.  Through the early to mid-1890’s, German troops fought various Nama, Herero, and
        Orlams groups in an effort to solidify German claims to the colony, eventually succeeding by
        1896, in some instances with the assistance of treaties (such as the German treaty with
        Hendrik Witbooi on behalf of the Orlam Namas).  Renewed Herero and Nama uprisings occurred
        between 1903-1907 (especially 1904), which were eventually put down after a brutal German
        military campaign of extermination in which 80% of the Herero population was killed.  
        Later, Germany faced continued challenges to its sovereignty in the northern parts of the
        colony, including from the Portuguese.  In 1908 German officials signed treaties with
        several Ovambo groups in northern Namibia. In the context of WWI, South African troops
        invaded and occupied German South West Africa from 1914 to 1915.  The German forces
        surrendered to the South Africans at the peace of Khorab on July 9, 1915, and South Africa
        imposed martial law on the same date. On December 7, 1920, in the context of the Treaty of
        Versailles, South West Africa was officially designated a League of Nations Class C mandate,
        to be administered by South Africa on behalf of the British crown (given South Africa’s
        status as a British dominion).  Following WWII and the termination of the League of Nations,
        the South African Government asserted that the League of Nations mandate had expired,
        refusing to submit South West Africa to the new United Nations Trusteeship system.  South
        Africa claimed sole authority over South West Africa following the demise of the League of
        Nations.  In the 1960’s, the name Namibia was increasingly used outside South Africa to
        refer to South West Africa, reflecting increasing international criticism of South Africa’s
        refusal to grant independence to Namibia/South West Africa.  Namibia became independent on
        March 21, 1990.</notes>
    <sources>
        <source>https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/wa.html</source>
        <source>https://www.britannica.com/place/Namibia</source>
    </sources>
</territory>
