<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<territory>
    <id>511</id>
    <old-id/>
    <short-form-name>Red Nation</short-form-name>
    <long-form-name>The Red Nation</long-form-name>
    <variants>
        <variant>
            <variant-id>511_1</variant-id>
            <variant-name>Great Namaqualand</variant-name>
            <valid-since type="pre-1776">1775</valid-since>
            <valid-until>1885</valid-until>
            <note/>
        </variant>
        <variant>
            <variant-id>511_1</variant-id>
            <variant-name>Namaland</variant-name>
            <valid-since type="pre-1776">1775</valid-since>
            <valid-until>1885</valid-until>
            <note/>
        </variant>
    </variants>
    <type-of-territory>independent-state</type-of-territory>
    <valid-since type="pre-1776">1775</valid-since>
    <valid-until>1885</valid-until>
    <exists-on-todays-map>false</exists-on-todays-map>
    <predecessors type="none"/>
    <successors>
        <successor rel="incorporation">510</successor>
    </successors>
    <notes>The precise names and tenures of these pre-colonial states are sometimes difficult to
        discern from the sources consulted, but in general, they correspond to the three major
        ethnic groups of pre-colonial (and present-day) Namibia: The Nama, Herero, and Ovambo (or
        Ambo). The Red Nation was a federation of six major Nama groups in southern Namibia,
        established in the 18th century and at its height exercising hegemony over the southern
        half of present-day Namibia. Groups from outside the Red Nation had to be granted permission
        to enter their territory. The Red Nation also collected tribute and signed treaties with
        Herero and other leaders (including the 1838 peace of Hoachanas). Some sources indicate the
        Red Nation relinquished its hegemony over other Nama tribes in an 1868 treaty, but
        references to the Red Nation continue thereafter, including sources stating that the Germans
        declared a protectorate over the Red Nation in 1885. 1885 has therefore been chosen as the
        rough end date for the Red Nation, though Nama groups continued to militarily resist German
        colonial claims into the early 1890’s, and Nama groups also participated in uprisings
        against German colonial rule in the first decade of the 20 th century. “Great Namaqualand”
        or Namaland referred more specifically to Nama areas in the southern third of present-day
        Namibia, and were also referenced in German protectorate agreements. Technically, there may
        have been “Namaqualand” or Nama states separate from or subsequent to the Red Nation (i.e.,
        extending somewhat past 1885), but they have been grouped together here in a single
        entry.</notes>
    <sources>
        <source>https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/wa.html</source>
        <source>https://www.britannica.com/place/Namibia</source>
    </sources>
</territory>
